<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-21T23:27:38-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">All The World is a Game</title><subtitle>Understanding the New Great Game between world powers. 
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Russia and the Qatar Crisis</title><link href="localhost:4000/russia/qatar/2017/06/25/Russias_Qatar-Crisis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia and the Qatar Crisis" /><published>2017-06-25T00:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-25T00:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/russia/qatar/2017/06/25/Russias_Qatar-Crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/russia/qatar/2017/06/25/Russias_Qatar-Crisis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/russia-flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Russia Flag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/flag-qatar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Qatar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is Russia’s Position on the Qatar Crisis?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rt.com/news/393960-uae-qatar-blockade-ultimatum/&quot;&gt;RT news piece&lt;/a&gt; ended by quoting the Director of Qatar’s government communications office, Sheikh Saif Al Thani “the illegal blockade has nothing to do with combating terrorism, it is about limiting Qatar’s sovereignty, and outsourcing our foreign policy.”  RT is to Russia what the NY Times is to the US - a voice of the Establishment.  It is safe to say that the Russian government agrees with the view of the RT article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian government also communicates with the public through Op-ed’s in Rt such as yesterday’s piece quoting Faruk Logoglu, former Turkish ambassador to the US &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rt.com/op-edge/393934-qatar-gulf-states-turkey/&quot;&gt;as saying&lt;/a&gt; “Qatar has experienced similar problems before, back in 2014. They were able to resolve those differences. I have a feeling that, despite the intensity and harsh and loud talk by the different parties over this crisis, that a solution will be found by the Arab states to this crisis”. And finally a TASS news piece &lt;a href=&quot;http://tass.com/politics/953171&quot;&gt;quoted a high-ranking member of the Russian Foreign Ministry as saying&lt;/a&gt; “We are for them to settle between themselves all the problems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s position is that the siege of Qatar has nothing to do with terrorism and that it is an internal matter to be decided by the GCC.  Despite this neutral stance Russia has many interests in Qatar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qatari investments in the Russian economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qatari co-operation in Oil and Gas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qatari support for Islamists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qatari support for rebels in Syria - now a moot point as the rebels have lost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar sits on a mammoth gas field shared with Iran. Like Iran, Qatar is a potential competitor in exporting gas to Europe. Qatar wanted a gas pipeline travelling through Syria to Europe which was blocked by Russia and, in part, led to the ongoing Syrian civil war.  It would seem that Russia and Qatar are enemies as they support opposing sides of the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia, however, follows the foreign policy of trying to turn enemies into neutrals so it would not be unusual if Russia saw this crisis as a means of improving their relationship with Qatar. Russia has strong relations with Iran, which is also a competitor in oil and gas so this issue is not a barrier to co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia would benefit from seeing Qatar cut ties with Islamist groups since Russia sees no difference between terrorists and Islamists.  The motivation for Russia to intervene in the Syrian Civil war is to keep Sunni Islamists/Terrorists from reaching Russia itself. Defeating them in Syria means not having to fight them in Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia would also benefit from Qatari investment in the Russian economy.  Siding with Qatar in the current crisis if they agree to cut or degrade their ties to Islamists would accomplish several goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move Qatar from enemy to neutral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce the power of Islamists and hence the threat to Russia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate investment in the Russian economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split the GCC and weaken the US-Empire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adopt the mediator role in the Middle East which lifts the profile of Russia world-wide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support Qatar, Russia would have to find a way to mediate the dispute. President Trump’s recent tweets blaming Qatar for terrorism have put the Empire in a poor position to act as mediator and have yielded that diplomatic ground to Russia. Look for Russia to step up it’s diplomatic efforts with the UAE and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Qatar is in the neutral category then the door is open to shift it to the ally category by entering into larger-scale and more strategic cooperation such as in the field of NatGas development and export.  Qatar drawing closer to Russia would also strengthen ties with Iran and Iraq. What do they all have in common?  Immense natural gas reserves.  A NatGas OPEC might become a possibility - one entirely free from the US-Empire.  The Empire knows this and would not allow it to happen and it is unlikely to remove it’s 10,000 troops from Qatar. We are getting ahead of ourselves here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stories in the MSM about Russia hacking Qatari government sites and how that started the current crisis seemed far-fetched at first and just another example of fake news. However, in light of the above four points, Russia has much to gain from this crisis and little to lose.  If Qatar remains steadfast and breaks with the GCC, it comes into play as a battleground state and Russia and others will compete for influence.  If Qatar capitulates, it means support for Islamist groups will end, which is in the benefit of Russia as well.  If Russia did not conduct the hacking themselves they must be feeling thankful that it happened anyways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What is Russia’s Position on the Qatar Crisis? An RT news piece ended by quoting the Director of Qatar’s government communications office, Sheikh Saif Al Thani “the illegal blockade has nothing to do with combating terrorism, it is about limiting Qatar’s sovereignty, and outsourcing our foreign policy.” RT is to Russia what the NY Times is to the US - a voice of the Establishment. It is safe to say that the Russian government agrees with the view of the RT article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Russia and US Strategies in Syria</title><link href="localhost:4000/us-empire/russia/iran/syria/2017/06/24/US-Russia-strategies-for-SE-Syria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia and US Strategies in Syria" /><published>2017-06-23T20:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-23T20:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/us-empire/russia/iran/syria/2017/06/24/US-Russia-strategies-for-SE-Syria</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/us-empire/russia/iran/syria/2017/06/24/US-Russia-strategies-for-SE-Syria.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the significance of the recent downing of the Su-22 in Syria by US proxies?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some possible motives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is preparing for a wider war by it’s proxies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is being vindictive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is trying to force Russia or Iran to retaliate and therefore justify a ground invasion of Syria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been four incidents in the past month around At-tanf (SE Syria) where the US-Empire has launched attacks on the government of Syria and it’s allies.  On the surface, this seems to suggest that the Empire is serious about it’s military intervention in Syria and is gradually increasing it’s presence - sort of invading in slow motion to avoid being noticed by its own public.  It would be tough to sway US public opinion in favour of another Mideast war, especially since President Trump’s supporters expected him to avoid another Mideast war. Invading quietly is not an effective strategy since the Empire’s enemies (Russia, Iran and Syria) are running at full speed.  Even though there have been four attacks in the past month by the Empire, they do not add up to a serious barrier to prevent the Syrian government from carrying out it’s military strategies considering the hundreds of thousands of soliders involved compared to the handful of casusalties from the Empire’s strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the downing of the Su-22, the US failed to talk with Russia over the de-confliction hotline set up for that reason. Russia called it being “stabbed in the back”.  Since the Empire is deliberatly firing upon Syrian government troops and their allies it may seem that they are widening the their role in the war.  On the surface that seems possible, but in reality the Empire doesnt have a ground force outside the Kurds in the North and therefore has little chance of gaining much ground. So 1) above is unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if Russia and Iran react to the attacks by attacking the Empire’s military, then that would create an opening through which President Trump would be pushed into war.  That would but the President in 
a dangerous place politically since he will be vulnerable on two fronts: a) losing control of the war to the Deep State and b) his already weak Presidency may not survive Americans coming home in body bags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is not likely that Russia or Iran will take the bait since they have nothing to gain from provoking an invasion by the Empire. Their best strategy is to continue what they are doing.  They have the initiative in the war and can concievably win back most of the Syrian territory with the exception of Idlib province and the Kurdish areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Russia, Iran and Syria routinely destroy forces supplied by the US-Empire - this includes ISIS - it is logical that the US-Empire would start doing that to forces supplied by Russia.  The Russian side is probably already doing the utmost to attack fighters allied or supplied by the US-Empire and it seems unlikely they could do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ll go with 2) above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What is the significance of the recent downing of the Su-22 in Syria by US proxies? Some possible motives: The US is preparing for a wider war by it’s proxies The US is being vindictive The US is trying to force Russia or Iran to retaliate and therefore justify a ground invasion of Syria</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Qatar Situation</title><link href="localhost:4000/qatar/us-empire/gcc/saudi/turkey/2017/06/16/Understanding-The-Qatar-Situation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Qatar Situation" /><published>2017-06-16T05:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T05:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/qatar/us-empire/gcc/saudi/turkey/2017/06/16/Understanding-The-Qatar-Situation</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/qatar/us-empire/gcc/saudi/turkey/2017/06/16/Understanding-The-Qatar-Situation.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/flag-qatar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Qatar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Muslim Brotherhood and other Islamist groups are a response to the backwards and repression of the Kings and Dictators of the Muslim World and the stagnation of the development of Muslim societies.   The Brotherhood represents revolutionary ideas about how Muslims should govern themselves, what kind of society they should live in and how the religion of Islam should guide them.  These ideas are necessary to break out of the centuries-old passivity of living under authoritarian regimes.  The Kings, Dictators and the US-Empire are frightened at such a conclusion since the awakening of the Muslim masses will reduce their power.  In the case of the Dictators it will eliminate their power completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas represented by the Muslim Brotherhood cannot be contained or killed. Muslim people will not give up their religion and enter into strict secularism because they are not at a stage of their development where that becomes a possibility and they want the opportunity to develop while incorporating, rather than sidelining, religion.  This will necessarily be a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Islamic revolution in Iran in 1979 was the first such attempt of introducing religion into the state apparatus.  Turkey’s election of Erdogan in 2003 represented the next major Muslim country to have an Islamist leader.  Tunisia’s revolt in 2011 which placed a democratically elected Islamist government in power was the first Arab example of an attempt to develop a Muslim governing structure.  The Egyptian revolution of 2011 was a third example and would have led the way for the entire Arab world to revolt and emerge past the era of Kings and Dictators but it was decapitated by the West in alliance with those same Kings and Dictators.  Currently the Islamist that was elected President is in jail in Egypt and the country is again run by a Dictator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The King in Qatar is one of the few authoritarian leaders that seems to understand that times are changing and it is neccessary to support Islamist groups and eventually break through this era of Kings and Dictators. This is fundamentally where Qatar finds itself in trouble with both the Kings and Dictators and the US-Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Trump, the Empire has put it’s full support behind Saudi Arabia and the UAE and set itself against the portion of Muslim people who want change - specifically Turks, Persians and some Arabs. (Though for cultural reasons many Arabs prefer Dictatorship). It is not just the Muslim Brotherhood and it’s sponsor in Qatar that are under threat but all Muslim people, Sunni or Shia, who want to develop and grow as societies. What will be accomplished by the Empire so solidly pitting itself against Muslim people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fundamental to human nature to develop, learn and grow.  The Muslim world cannot do so under Dictators and Kings.  The drive to develop creates pressure from the population upwards to the leadership of Muslim countries.  By supporting the Kings and Dicatators, the US-Empire is trying to cap this pressure.  Will it work?  Trying to deny or supress human nature is unlikely to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To even try such a thing displays the blindness of the US-Empire and the inability of the current President to understand the world around him.  The Empire is blinded by arrogance as over the centuries the West has become accustomed to doing as it pleases in the Muslim world and killing with impunity.  President Trump is blinded by his own ignorance.  The Empire and it’s President see Muslims as backwards and as a lesser people; they are filled with rage towards Muslims since 9/11.  This attitude leads to several mistakes understanding reality and therefore leads to inappropriate strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Empire over-estimates it’s ability to control Muslim people and countries by under-estimating their capabilities.  The Iraq war in 2003 was based on the idea that the Empire could contorl the aftermath of that war which it failed to do, losing the post-war competition to Iran. The Israeli invasion of Lebanon in 2006 to destroy Hezbollah clearly under-estimated that group and caused a humiliation for Israel.  The attempt since 2011 to overthrow Syrian President Assad by training and arming terrorist groups (even the same group responsible for 9/11) has also been a failure. Even if one considers that the foreign policy of the Empire towards the Middle East may be one of purposely trying to destory countries and create chaos as revenge for 9/11, the Empire is doing a very poor job of managing the chaos which has lead to massive strategic errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, the Middle East was completely under the tutelage of the Empire with one rebellious Dictator in Iraq and a non-aligned Syria.  In 2017, Lebanon, Syria and Iraq are all solidly in the Iranian/Russian camp and have been flipped away from the US-Empire with Turkey and Qatar on their way out too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Muslims as lowly creatures means that the Empire is not able to appreciate the truly revolutionary struggles of Islamists against Kings and Dictators. They cannot see it for what it is: the human spirit desiring to be free, indpendent and have the opportunity to grow however it chooses.  To see it like this would require that the Empire first see Muslims as humans which is not possible espeically under President Trump.  President Obama saw it and that is why he wanted to strike a deal with Iran - he actually wanted to pivot away from the Kings and Dictators and towards the Islamist governments of Turkey and Iran.  He was also willing - for a time - to allow the Dictator of Egypt to fall and be replaced by democratically elected Islamists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently the strategy of the Empire is to sponsor Saudi Arabia to create some sort of Arab NATO to face Iran.  This collection of Kings and Dictators (SA, UAE, Egypt and some less important countries) can never win a war (see the current state of the Yemen war and the long history of Arab military humilations).  Nonetheless, this is the new strategy of the Empire and it is worse than the previous ones over the last 17 years. One can be certain that in the coming years, the power of Iran and Russia in the Middle East will be consolidated.  This will dovetail nicely into the the plans of China to create a belt of trade routes connecting Europe and Asia.  The Iranian/Russian controlled Middle East will be pivotal to Eurasian integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Background The Muslim Brotherhood and other Islamist groups are a response to the backwards and repression of the Kings and Dictators of the Muslim World and the stagnation of the development of Muslim societies. The Brotherhood represents revolutionary ideas about how Muslims should govern themselves, what kind of society they should live in and how the religion of Islam should guide them. These ideas are necessary to break out of the centuries-old passivity of living under authoritarian regimes. The Kings, Dictators and the US-Empire are frightened at such a conclusion since the awakening of the Muslim masses will reduce their power. In the case of the Dictators it will eliminate their power completely.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the strategy of the US-Empire?</title><link href="localhost:4000/iran/iraq/lebanon/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/israel/2017/06/11/Wha-is-the-US-Strategy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the strategy of the US-Empire?" /><published>2017-06-11T09:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-11T09:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/iran/iraq/lebanon/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/israel/2017/06/11/Wha-is-the-US-Strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/iran/iraq/lebanon/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/israel/2017/06/11/Wha-is-the-US-Strategy.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/us-flag.gif&quot; alt=&quot;US&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach of the US-Empire towards the world and specifically the Middle East has shifted.  Wheras President Obama was restrained in dealing with Arab dictators, preferring to dabble in cooperation with Islamists, President Trump is supporting these dictators like never before - totally un-restrained. Trump also equates political Islam with terrorism and seems to have been conviced that organizations like the Muslim Brotherhood need to be eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this shift comes from the nature of Donald Trump: sudden and seemingly impulsive shifts pushed heavily on twitter and apparently without building consensus in the State or Defense Departments and more widely the National Security establishment.  Trump at first seemed to blame Qatar for terrorism on twitter, then we learn that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theamericanconservative.com/larison/tillerson-scrambles-to-undo-trumps-qatar-blunder/&quot;&gt;Secretary of State Tillerson is trying to de-escalate the situation&lt;/a&gt;. Sudden shifts in policy don’t work because there is a lot of preparation that is needed from a variety of government agenices. Sudden shifts indicate a lack of actual strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this shift can also be attributed to thinking among his Iran-hawk cabinet and the Deep State.  They are all Iran hawks, Islam-hawks and Israel-firsters: both the cabinet and the deep state.  They only good muslim to them is an obseqious dictator who will kill as many of his own as desired by the US-Empire.  Free-thinking people who may cause the Muslim world to develop and evolve are to be eliminated as they represent a threat to power in the region.  The Empire already tried to overthrow the Islamist President Erdogan in Turkey and would love to do the same in Iran and replace both of them with compliant non-democratic military regimes.  So what is the strategy to get this done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the 9/11 attacks the strategy we can discern in hindsight was to take Iraq and Afghanistan and have Iran encircled. This was the plan in 2003.  It did not work out because after the military invasion of Iraq, Iran won the political and diplomatic battle afterwards and successfully installed it’s supporters in the Iraqi government.  Iraq was flipped away from the US-Empire and into the Iran-Russia axis.  This was a geo-strategic loss of epic proportions for the US-Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next attempt was to eliminate the Iran-backed Hezbollah from Lebanaon.  Then National Security Advisor Condoleeza Rice was famous for her “birthpangs of a new Middle East” remark when commenting on the 2006 Israeli invasion of Lebanon.  It did not work out that way as Hizbollah was able to sucessfully defend itself and Israel had to withdraw.  The “birthpangs” were not of a new US-Empire led Middle East of compliant dictators but of the emergence of the new Iran-Russia axis in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came the invasion of Syria by proxy:  The Empire used Saudi Arabia and Turkey to create and fund Islamic terrorist groups to overthrow President Bashar Al-Assad in Syria. This too has not worked out and the Empire has essentially lost.  Although it might try to cut up Syria into pieces, it will not depose Bashar Al-Assad, nor prevent Russia and Iran from establishing a permanent military presence in what remains of Syria.  As a result, Lebanon, Syria and Iraq are all allied with Iran, with Russia providing the hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the next attempt at breaking Iranian-Russian power - after failing three times - is to fund Saudi Arabia to do it by creating an Arab-NATO.  Where America failed (Iraq) and Isreal failed (Lebanon) and terrorists failed (Syria) the new strategy is to expect Saudi Arabia and other Sunni Arab states like Egypt to succeed.  The first step is to get all Arab states aligned - hence the pressure on Qatar to drop it’s ties to Iran and to other Islamists such as the Muslim Brotherhood, Turkey and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Muslim Brotherhood types (e.g. Islamists from Turkey to Tunisia) have to be opposed because Islamists are thinkers and revolutionaaries and they have an affinity for Iran rather than an aversion. Therefore, they also have a enmity for all Arab dictators - that is why they are hated so much by Saudi Arabia and the rest of the GCC. So the Sunni world must be cleansed of thinkers and aligned in a unified, slavish, anti-Iran alliance.  Then they will do what? Attack Iran?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fourth effort by the US-Empire to attack Iran and hence Russia since it is aligned to Iran, has further strategic implications. If they are successful in creating a Sunni Arab NATO, attacking Islamists supporters such as Qatar necessarily pushes Turkey closer to Iran since both countries have ties to Islamists groups and good relations to Qatar.  In fact, both countries have come out strong in support of Qatar after the GCC announced it’s blockade. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rferl.org/a/iran-planes-qatar-food-aid-blockade/28540876.html&quot;&gt;Iran has been provding planeloads of food to Qatar&lt;/a&gt; and a review of the government friendly Daily Sabah newspaper reveals a distinct &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailysabah.com/op-ed&quot;&gt;pro-Qatar bias&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey is already concerned over the US-Kurd alliance.  Turkey also knows it is no longer a part of the West or welcome in NATO or the EU.  Turkey joining Iran and Russia seems the logical alternative for them.  Perhaps one day they will consider joining the SCO.  Entering the SCO along with Iran would be an elegant way to enter that institution since both countries would counter-balance each other like recent entrants Pakistan and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from pushing Iran and Turkey closer together, the new strategy of attacking Iran through an Arab NATO has another flaw: Arab dictators always lose wars.  This is a Truth.  Arabs only fight well for Islam.  Without Islam they will not fight but run away.  See the long history of Sunni Arab losses under dictatroships.  The only Sunni Arabs that fight well are Al-Nusra and associated terrorist groups.  They are the Sunni equivalent of Hizbullah.  The only way Sunni Arab countries become effective fighting forces is if they can leverage Islam as a source of motivation.  Purging Islamists from Sunni countries will ensure many military losses to come.  I don’t think that Iran and Russia are sweating very much after having faced down the US in Syria when they are threatened with an Arab NATO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a look at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unz.com/tsaker/the-crisis-in-qatar/&quot;&gt;great article by the Saker&lt;/a&gt; which takes a similar angle on things as this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The approach of the US-Empire towards the world and specifically the Middle East has shifted. Wheras President Obama was restrained in dealing with Arab dictators, preferring to dabble in cooperation with Islamists, President Trump is supporting these dictators like never before - totally un-restrained. Trump also equates political Islam with terrorism and seems to have been conviced that organizations like the Muslim Brotherhood need to be eliminated. Part of this shift comes from the nature of Donald Trump: sudden and seemingly impulsive shifts pushed heavily on twitter and apparently without building consensus in the State or Defense Departments and more widely the National Security establishment. Trump at first seemed to blame Qatar for terrorism on twitter, then we learn that Secretary of State Tillerson is trying to de-escalate the situation. Sudden shifts in policy don’t work because there is a lot of preparation that is needed from a variety of government agenices. Sudden shifts indicate a lack of actual strategy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Syrian War Winds Down: South Syria</title><link href="localhost:4000/iran/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/2017/06/10/The-Syrian-War_Winds_Down.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Syrian War Winds Down: South Syria" /><published>2017-06-10T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-10T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/iran/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/2017/06/10/The-Syrian-War_Winds_Down</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/iran/russia/turkey/syria/us-empire/2017/06/10/The-Syrian-War_Winds_Down.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/syria-flag.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Syria&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The de-confliction zones initiated by Russia have remained in place indicating that all parties wish to see an end to the war. The Assad regime will stay, the Kurds will have a full state or autonomous zone, Iran and Russia will have a military and strategic presence permanently in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The losers in this war will be mainly the ones who started it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turkey will see a powerful Kurdish zone that will be a threat to it’s security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Israel-US-Saudi axis will have to live with the reality of the militaries of Iran and Russia active Syria which was not the case prior to the war. This will severly restrict the freedom of movement of Israel - they won’t be able to attack Lebanon or any other place whenever they feel like as they did in 2006.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ISIS will be eliminated but the frustration of Sunni Arabs in the region will not be. This will be an ongoing challenge to the state of Syria.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syria will lose in the aftermath of this war as the country will never be whole again. The areas along the Israeli border and the Idlib province will have to be brought back into Syria through a political process which may not yield a unified Syria. The Kurdish regions will not return.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US-Empire will gain a position with the Kurds in the North of Syria which will free it from having to deal with Turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;South Syria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-large&quot; src=&quot;https://southfront.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/1-128.jpg?x43560&quot; alt=&quot;Southfront map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://southfront.org/strategic-implications-of-syrian-government-forces-success-at-border-with-iraq/&quot;&gt;Map source: Southfront&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In south Syria, the US-Empire is holding the Al-Tanaf border crossing between Iraq and Syria.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://elijahjm.wordpress.com/2017/06/08/isis-dropping-as-fast-as-it-grew-in-2014-the-us-begins-to-attack-isis-in-raqqah-whilst-iraqi-forces-advance-behind-the-american-lines/&quot;&gt;Elijah Magnier &lt;/a&gt;has it that the purpose of this move is to force the Syrian Arab Army to the northern border crossing of Al-Bukamal which is an area that ISIS fighters fleeing Raqqah will have to cross.  The SAA will have to fight them and it will be bloody.  The US-Empire will eventually have to vacate Al-Tanaf due to the fact that it is surrounded on all sides including the Iraqi side by forces loyal to or allied with the Syrian government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of looking at the situation is that the US-Empire may have wanted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://southfront.org/strategic-implications-of-syrian-government-forces-success-at-border-with-iraq/&quot;&gt;train Sunni Arab forces to strike northward from Al-Tanaf&lt;/a&gt; and try to take more of the border area including Al-Bukamal.  If that is so, then the recent SAA move to take Al-Bukamal would cut off the Empire’s plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have said in previous posts, the major players have reverted to their basic goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Russia: fight Sunni terrorsits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turkey: prevent Kurds from gaining a state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US-Empire: protect Israel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iran: consolidate Shia power/stand up to the US-Empire due to their revolutionary ideology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syria: it’s territorial integrity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Empire has no serious strategy or mission in Al-Tanaf with respect to protecting Israel.  Trying to control Syria and Iraq and therefore mitigating Iran’s presence in this theatre by controlling one border post is hopeless.  Consider that Iran was able to help build Hezbollah in Lebanon through all the years that it’s mortal enemy Saddam Hussein was in power in Iraq and land routes through that country were completely closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few weeks or months we will probably see an attempt by the US-Empire to grab control over land in the area of Syria that is bordering Israel in order to create a buffer zone.  That would be the only worthwhile project for the US-Empire at this point aside from it’s realationship with the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the details of how the south of Syria winds down, it is clear that the US-Empire will not be a major player.  The four countries of Iran, Iraq, Syria and Lebanon will be connected by road at a time when they are all allies and share a Shia-muslim identity.  This is new in the history of the region and a major loss on the Middle-Eastern chessboard for the US-Empire as these countries are not aligned with the Empire. They are all a mixture of sovereign states and/or part of a military coalition with Russia. All states have armed groups that cooperate with one another: The Lebanese Hizbullah, the Syrian military, the Popular Mobilization Units (PMUs) in Iraq and the various arms of the Iranian military. All now have experience fighting alongside one another and all share a Shia-muslim identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategic importance of this land bridge cannot be over-stated.  It will create an opportunity for the region to be the land bridge to Europe that is necessary for China’s OBOR initiative.  This region may choose to integrate with that project and hence become a part of the Eurasian axis instead of cooperating with the US-Empire.  This region also includes massive oil and gas resources in Iraq and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The de-confliction zones initiated by Russia have remained in place indicating that all parties wish to see an end to the war. The Assad regime will stay, the Kurds will have a full state or autonomous zone, Iran and Russia will have a military and strategic presence permanently in Syria. The losers in this war will be mainly the ones who started it: Turkey will see a powerful Kurdish zone that will be a threat to it’s security Israel-US-Saudi axis will have to live with the reality of the militaries of Iran and Russia active Syria which was not the case prior to the war. This will severly restrict the freedom of movement of Israel - they won’t be able to attack Lebanon or any other place whenever they feel like as they did in 2006. ISIS will be eliminated but the frustration of Sunni Arabs in the region will not be. This will be an ongoing challenge to the state of Syria. Syria will lose in the aftermath of this war as the country will never be whole again. The areas along the Israeli border and the Idlib province will have to be brought back into Syria through a political process which may not yield a unified Syria. The Kurdish regions will not return. The US-Empire will gain a position with the Kurds in the North of Syria which will free it from having to deal with Turkey.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Qatar Holds Strong</title><link href="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/russia/turkey/2017/06/08/Qatar-Holds-Strong.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Qatar Holds Strong" /><published>2017-06-08T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-08T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/russia/turkey/2017/06/08/Qatar-Holds-Strong</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/russia/turkey/2017/06/08/Qatar-Holds-Strong.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/flag-qatar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Qatar&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/thani.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Al-Thani&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Empire made it’s move yesterday indirectly attacking Iran by trying to remove one of it’s supporters (not quite allies) from the Middle-Eastern chessboard.  The move may have been instigated by Saudi Arabia but the recent visit to that country by Donald Trump and his administration’s blatant anti-Iran bias make it certain that the US was itself involved in the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/erdogan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Erdogan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Turkish response&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey has met with the Foreign Minister of Iran.  No details were released but it is not a coincedence that they met at this time.  They spoke of gathering for a “High Level Cooperation Council meeting” soon. Considering the timing, it speaks of a new cooperation between Iran and Turkey. Elsewhere it is being reported that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rferl.org/a/turkey-iran-back-qatar-dispute-saudi-arabia-other-arab-states/28535012.html&quot;&gt;Turkey has thrown it’s weight behind Qatar&lt;/a&gt; by sending troops and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-small&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/lavrov.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lavrov&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Russian response&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russian FM Lavrov has scheduled a meeting with Qatari FM Al-Thani on Saturday.  The fact that this meeting was set up before any meeting with US President Trump shows quite clearly where Qatar’s loyalties lie.  Despite hosting 10,000 American troops, Qatar seems oddly on the the Russia/Iran axis rather than with the US-Empire.  It seems the countries which are developing a political Islam such as Turkey and Iran have more in common with Qatar (sponsor of the Muslim Brotherhood) than with other Arab Kingdoms.&lt;br /&gt;
Russia does not seem to have taken a side yet.  Their words on the crisis do not indicate that they will committ anything to help Qatar. Lavrov spoke of the need for &lt;a href=&quot;https://ria.ru/world/20170608/1496094608.html&quot;&gt;“require consolidation rather than separation”&lt;/a&gt; in fighting terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar is not capitulating - far from it.  It has powerful friends, money and doesn’t seem to mind bucking the trends of the GCC.  What will happen next?  How can Qatar move towards Iran/Russia when they host 10,000 US troops?  The support Qatar has already recieved gives it breathing room to negotiate with Saudi Arabia and the UAE.  In the end, my guess would be that Iran would lose something in this confrontation.  Iran is what this is all about anyways.  The demands put upon Qatar are all fake, if they agree to distance themselves from Iran, then this whole show will end.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The US-Empire made it’s move yesterday indirectly attacking Iran by trying to remove one of it’s supporters (not quite allies) from the Middle-Eastern chessboard. The move may have been instigated by Saudi Arabia but the recent visit to that country by Donald Trump and his administration’s blatant anti-Iran bias make it certain that the US was itself involved in the plan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Empire Strikes Back</title><link href="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/2017/06/07/All-About-Iran.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Empire Strikes Back" /><published>2017-06-07T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/2017/06/07/All-About-Iran</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/iran/2017/06/07/All-About-Iran.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/iran_flag.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Iran&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s All About Iran&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Empire is on the offensive.  On June 6th, it struck a Syrian military target around the At-tanf border crossing which re-affirmed its positoin as occupier of southeastern Syria. On the same day, it’s client, Saudi Arabia led a total embargo on Qatar for wanting better relations with Iran. On June 7th, a terrorist attack targeted the parliament in Tehran. This last one could not have been a coincidence, it must have been coordinated with the other two to send a message to Iran:  the Empire is coming after you. Logically, one would expect this sort of action since the Trump administration is packed with Iran hawks.  It was just a matter of time, and now it begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Obama administration, an attempt was made to distance the Empire from Sunni despots like Hosni Mubarak in Egypt and the King of Saudi Arabia and to pivot towards a Iran with the Nuclear deal.  Now under Trump, these dictators have been embraced, supplied with weapons and directed at Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three attacks are generally bad news for Iran since they herald a period in which the US Empire is going on the offensive wheras it was Iran and Russia that had been on the offensive for several years in Iraq and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian military wants the At-tanf border crossing but in order to get it, they will need Russian and Iranian help.  So far, we have not seen any sign that Russia is willing to committ serious military hardware such as jets or anti-aircraft missiles to provide cover for the Syrian military.  The Empire is winning this battle but the strategic value of At-tanf is questionable. Iran does not need the At-tanf crossing to communicate with it’s allies in Damascus or Beirut although it would be helpful to them.  For years, the built up Hezbollah and had a cooperative relationship with the Syrian government at a time when the whole of Iraq was a no-go zone for Iran. The Empire’s rationale to stop Iran/Syria from getting this border point is probably to deny a resource rather than the impossible goal of cutting Iran off from it’s allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar is in a tough spot.  The embargo placed upon them creates huge problems for their economy and the list of 10 demands from Saudi Arabia to lift the embargo is humiliating and impossible to implement.  Qatar is on the verge of being invaded by Saudi Arabia and is hoping for Turkish support.  If Qatar is eliminated by Saudi Arabia, it will not have much effect on the ground in Syria.  It will remove a neutral power from the GCC and thus bias that organization towards a completely anti-Iran line. On the other hand, if Qatar survives this, the GCC is effectively broken.  Saudi Arabia has made huge gambles recently: crashing the price of oil, starting a war in Yemen and now embargoing Qatar.  The first two did not work and probably the third won’t either. Everything hinges on Turkish and Iranian support of Qatar in the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump is keen to create an anti-Iran alliance among Sunni despotic regimes and is willing to give Saudi Arabia all the weapons it needs to do so. This has been tried before - the US supported Saddam Hussein to attack Iran in 1980 which had disastrous consquences for both sides but the war was eventually won by Iran.  Iran went on to become a regional power while Iraq was eventually obliterated.  It is unlikely that the leadership in Washington will learn from history and putting any policy, especially a war policy, in the hands of Saudi Arabia is sure to backfire badly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s All About Iran The US Empire is on the offensive. On June 6th, it struck a Syrian military target around the At-tanf border crossing which re-affirmed its positoin as occupier of southeastern Syria. On the same day, it’s client, Saudi Arabia led a total embargo on Qatar for wanting better relations with Iran. On June 7th, a terrorist attack targeted the parliament in Tehran. This last one could not have been a coincidence, it must have been coordinated with the other two to send a message to Iran: the Empire is coming after you. Logically, one would expect this sort of action since the Trump administration is packed with Iran hawks. It was just a matter of time, and now it begins.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Saudia Arabia moves against Qatar</title><link href="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/2017/06/05/Arab-Nato.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saudia Arabia moves against Qatar" /><published>2017-06-05T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-05T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/2017/06/05/Arab-Nato</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/gcc/saudi/qatar/2017/06/05/Arab-Nato.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/flag-qatar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Qatar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump went to Saudi Arabia recently and &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.cbc.ca/1.4125552.1495305137!/fileImage/httpImage/image.jpg_gen/derivatives/original_620/usa-trump-saudi.jpg&quot;&gt;sword-danced &lt;/a&gt;and “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/22/world/middleeast/trump-glowing-orb-saudi.html&quot;&gt;Orb-ed&lt;/a&gt;” with their leaders and sold them hundreds of billions of dollars of military equipment.  What did he think they would do with that money? Fight terrorism?  Since terrorism is a tool of the US Empire’s global military strategy and means of attempted regime change in Syria, that was not a likley outcome. The military equipment is meant to be used against Shia Muslims from the Houthis in Yemen, to the Persians in Iran - especially Iran.  The Trump administration is filled with Iran hawks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the orders have been given: Saudi Arabia is to try and put together an Arab NATO to threaten Iran with and save US troops from having to get into harms away. Today, Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, the UAE and Egypt have all severed diplomatic and economic ties with Qatar, a small nation with a population less than Houston, Tx but sitting on massive oil and gas reserves.  Qatar’s only land border through which it imports almost all of it’s food is with Saudi Arabia and is now closed.  What was Qatar’s crime?  It violated the unity of GCC states and more widely Arab states by openly saying it would like better relations with Iran.  Qatar is now being punished for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qatar hosts the Empire’s CENTCOM and a small Turkish base.  Since about 10,000 US troops are stationed in Qatar, it is unlikely anything happens in that country without the Empire knowing about it.  The Empire knows very well what Saudi Arabia is doing and it approves of this pressure on the Qatari leadership.  The only way Qatar can survive this is to find other supporters that might intervene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mfa.gov.tr/no_-175_-5-june-2017_press-release-regarding-the-developments-among-saudi-arabia_-united-arab-emirates_-bahrain_-egypt-and-qatar.en.mfa&quot;&gt;response of the Turkish Ministry of Foreign Affairs&lt;/a&gt; has been soft - just a call for a “swift resolution” a reminder that terrorism can only be dealt with through “unity” and “solidarity”. Turkish foreign policy has been convoluted for some time but lately it is becoming exceedingly simple due to the rise of the Kurds in Syria and their support from the US.  Turkey needs to cut down the Kurds and that is their only priority. Although they would like to see better relations with Iran, they are unlikely to make any move to save Qatar.  They, like the Russians know that Qatar and the other Sunni Arab countries are on the US Empire’s side and cannot be flipped away.  Therefore, the sqaubble between SA and Qatar is seen as an internal affair.  As the Russian foreign minister Sergey Lavrov says, it is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://sputniknews.com/middleeast/201706051054319507-lavrov-russia-qatar-middle-east/&quot;&gt;their business&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/qatar-map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Qatar map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting SA to set up an Arab NATO to implement the Empire’s foreign policy is in-line with President Donald Trump’s priorites of avoiding US troop committments to the Middle East.  Trump launched criticisms of the real NATO - especially Germany - for not doing their fair share and paying more money for their security.  Trump wants to delegate and hand over more responsibility for security to other nations and therefore reduce the size and burden of the US Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting other countries to implement the Empire’s foreign policy comes with it’s risks as well.  In Syria, the Empire tried to arm jihadis to accomplish the goal of toppling Presdent Assad.  Theses jihadis became ISIS.  These jihadis came back to bite the Empire in Europe and Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the Empire hopes to use Arab despots instead of jihadis to implement it’s foreign policy goal of confronting Iran. It is ironic that this Arab NATO, supported by the US Empire, is entirely composed of dicatatorial regimes and is not supported by any Arab country that has regular elections (Tunisia and Lebanon) and is aimed at an Iran that recently held an election for their Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Donald Trump went to Saudi Arabia recently and sword-danced and “Orb-ed” with their leaders and sold them hundreds of billions of dollars of military equipment. What did he think they would do with that money? Fight terrorism? Since terrorism is a tool of the US Empire’s global military strategy and means of attempted regime change in Syria, that was not a likley outcome. The military equipment is meant to be used against Shia Muslims from the Houthis in Yemen, to the Persians in Iran - especially Iran. The Trump administration is filled with Iran hawks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Syria: De-escalation Zones</title><link href="localhost:4000/us-empire,/syria,/russia/2017/05/10/Syria-De-escalation-Zones.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Syria: De-escalation Zones" /><published>2017-05-10T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/us-empire,/syria,/russia/2017/05/10/Syria-De-escalation-Zones</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/us-empire,/syria,/russia/2017/05/10/Syria-De-escalation-Zones.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-large&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/2017-05-05-brief01-eng.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Syria De-escalation Zone map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;http://eng.mil.ru/en/news_page/country/more.htm?id=12121964@egNews&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Larger version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the De-escalation zones proposed by Russia?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De-escalation zones are areas of Syria in which all parties to the agreement will cease fighting each other.  The agreement is in the form of a Memorandum of Understanding and it does not include ISIS and Al-Nusra (by whatever name it currently uses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://eng.mil.ru/en/news_page/country/more.htm?id=12121964@egNews&quot;&gt;The Russian Ministry of Defence&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Zone 1:   The first zone is the most extensive located in the north of Syria. It includes the Idlib province as well as north-eastern areas of the Latakia province, western areas of the Aleppo province, and northern areas of the Hama province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 2:  The second one is in the north of the Homs province. It includes al-Rastan and Tell Bisa as well as nearest areas controlled by the opposition groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 3:  The third one is Eastern Ghouta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 4:  The fourth zone is located in the south of Syria and includes areas of the Daraa and Quneitra provinces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within two weeks, representatives of state-guarantors will form a Joint working group. The group will present borders of the de-escalation zones and safety lanes as well as maps for separating formations of armed opposition from terrorist groupings by July 4, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is to be stressed that signing of the Memorandum on creation of the de-escalation zones in the Syrian Arab Republic does not stop fighting against terrorists of the ISIS and Jabhat al-Nusra in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State-guarantors undertake to continue fighting against formations of these and other terrorist organizations in the de-escalation zones as well as provide assistance to the government troops and armed opposition in fighting insurgents in other areas of Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After establishing of the de-escalation zones, the government troops will be sent to continue offensive on the ISIS formations in the central and eastern parts of Syria as well as to liberate areas located along the River Euphrates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russian Aerospace Forces will support these actions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colonel General Sergei Rudskoy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“De-escalation zones will allow the government troops to release many units. The Russian Aerospace Forces will continue supporting the Syrian Armed Forces while eliminating illegal armed groups of the ISIL international terrorist organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main efforts will focused on the development of the offensive in the east from Palmyra and further lifting a siege of the Deir ez-Zor city.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fighting against ISIS and Nusra will continue even in the de-escalation zones&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The formation of these zones is a tactic to focus the fight towards the east of Syria - same place as the US is heading.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How will Russia be able to separate Nusra from the rest in Idlib?  Effectively, it means that Nusra will be left alone. The fight will head east to ISIS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The de-escalation zone agreement means that all the major players have decided to keep what they have and stop fighting for more except with respect to areas controlled by ISIS.  Turkey along with Nusra have Idlib province plus some small areas along the Turkish border.  Turkey has abandoned any goal of controlling more areas and would like to direct their attention towards reducing the position of the Kurds on the Syrian chessboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  Empire’s attempted coup against Erdogan made cooperation impossible and coordinated support of Sunni rebels/terrorists has been eliminated.  Therefore, the Assad-must-go policy ended some time ago.  In the aftermath of the coup attempt, Turkey gave up Aleppo province and also stopped supporting any further advance of Nusra and others under an agreement with Russia.  In return, Turkey was allowed to go after the Kurds and launch a ground invasion into an area of North Syria that split the Kurd areas in two portions, halted their advance and reduced their power.  That was some time ago and since then the situation in the North has stabilized.  The de-escalation zone is then a logical fit for the ground reality.  Idlib province’s re-integration into Syria will become a political problem to be solved at some later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 4 in the south is acceptable to Israel since it effectively means that Hezbollah and Iranian troops will not be entering the south of Syria to start a second front against them (Lebanon being the first).  This situation will hold until the fighting in the East is settled.  Since Syrian and other troops will not be moving into the area, it gives an opening to the Empire to exert more effort to control the area.  Like Turkey, the Empire has been reduced to focus on it’s primary concern.  For Turkey it is the threat of the Kurds, for the Empire it is the security of Israel.  Neither the Empire nor Turkey are interested any longer in Syria as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is left?  The Empire must decide if keeping Iran and Hezbollah out of the South of Syria is enough, or do they want to fight for a presence in East Syria … which would mean confronting Russia directly?  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonofalabama.org/2017/05/syria-the-regime-will-be-there-us-to-concede-raqqa-and-the-syrian-east-.html&quot;&gt;Moonofalabama&lt;/a&gt; is reporting via a Neocon &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/kurd-led-force-homes-in-on-isis-bastion-with-assent-of-u-s-and-syria-alike-1494522632&quot;&gt;WSJ&lt;/a&gt; piece that the Empire might have calculated that it is best to not bother with East Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Empire launched the war against Syria in the the hope of toppling Assad and flipping Syria to the Empire’s side. This hope was the fundamental reason for fighting this war -  it has now been extinguished.   For it’s trouble, Turkey won a piece of Syria (Idlib) and inherited two headaches: that Idlib is controlled by Al-Qaeda/Al-Nusra and that the Kurds are several steps closer to having a large state of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Empire has gained control over a piece of South Syria for the protection of Israel but for that it has incurred some headaches of it’s own: during the course of the war Iranian troops and Hezbollah received valuable field experience and are now battle-hardened and operating in places they had not seen previously.  Neither Hezbollah nor Iran were present in South Syria before the war. Hezbollah and the Syrian and Iranian military’s have higher morale, experience coordinating with one another and with Russia as well.  None of these things existed before the war.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Larger version What are the De-escalation zones proposed by Russia? De-escalation zones are areas of Syria in which all parties to the agreement will cease fighting each other. The agreement is in the form of a Memorandum of Understanding and it does not include ISIS and Al-Nusra (by whatever name it currently uses). From The Russian Ministry of Defence: “Zone 1: The first zone is the most extensive located in the north of Syria. It includes the Idlib province as well as north-eastern areas of the Latakia province, western areas of the Aleppo province, and northern areas of the Hama province.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">China and North Korea</title><link href="localhost:4000/china,/north-korea/2017/04/26/China-North-Korea.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China and North Korea" /><published>2017-04-26T14:06:20-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-26T14:06:20-04:00</updated><id>localhost:4000/china,/north-korea/2017/04/26/China-North-Korea</id><content type="html" xml:base="localhost:4000/china,/north-korea/2017/04/26/China-North-Korea.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-images-medium&quot; src=&quot;localhost:4000/assets/nk_flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;NK Flag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;China’s Strategy with North Korea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea is a client or pawn of China. &lt;a href=&quot;http://thediplomat.com/2016/03/why-china-north-korea-relations-cant-be-broken/&quot;&gt;Similar to how Saudi Arabia is a pawn of the American Empire, North Korea is a pawn of China despite being disrespected and disliked&lt;/a&gt;. North Korea’s strategic importance prevails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North Korea has historically acted as a buffer between U.S.-controlled South Korea and mainland China.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cfr.org/north-korea/costs-benefits-chinas-relationship-north-korea/p30887&quot;&gt;The Chinese intervened in the Korean war because they felt there was a chance the U.S. would invade China&lt;/a&gt; via North Korea at the time. The fear continued for decades until today.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North Korea is able to do things - such as threaten the American Empire or Japan - that China cannot do by itself without risking it’s international reputation.  China’s ideology focuses on being the number one economy in the world and for that it needs to promote global trade which it cannot do if it is seen as an unstable, threatening country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, China may fear that ending it’s relationship with North Korea may produce a unified Korea partnered with the American Empire and thus giving the Empire the ability to place troops right at the border with China. China sees what is happening to Russia and knows it’s history and does not trust the Empire to be so close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia is the ideological driver of Islamic extremism which in the end caused the 9/11 attack.  Some in the US may have wanted to punish Saudi Arabia but in the end nothing happened. Similarly North Korea can do just about anything without fear of repirisal from China including develop nuclear and other weapons and fire missiles here or there.  The mental instability of the leaders of Saudi Arabia and North Korea are from the same root cause - being spoiled pawns of their respective masters. They sometimes get out of control and create headaches but they do not present real threats to their masters - just other countries.  Saudi Arabia is a threat to Syria, Iraq and Iran and North Korea is a threat to South Korea and Japan.  Since neither China or the U.S. is threatened by their own pawns, they will do nothing about them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">China’s Strategy with North Korea North Korea is a client or pawn of China. Similar to how Saudi Arabia is a pawn of the American Empire, North Korea is a pawn of China despite being disrespected and disliked. North Korea’s strategic importance prevails. North Korea has historically acted as a buffer between U.S.-controlled South Korea and mainland China. The Chinese intervened in the Korean war because they felt there was a chance the U.S. would invade China via North Korea at the time. The fear continued for decades until today. North Korea is able to do things - such as threaten the American Empire or Japan - that China cannot do by itself without risking it’s international reputation. China’s ideology focuses on being the number one economy in the world and for that it needs to promote global trade which it cannot do if it is seen as an unstable, threatening country.</summary></entry></feed>